he
ah
[Music]
hello and good evening everybody good
evening good day wherever you are I hope
you're all doing great and welcome to
the ask show it's been a long time since
we did an episode that's dedicated
solely to science and physics and all of
that good stuff so before we go as is
usual let me greet you all let's see who
all is there on the live stream I can
see gusai gusai Forum Karan naat baby
cheeks Tanish Kumar Lou ma zong Amisha
hello Atul SES toan CH pratik V Marisha
pitra yosra Yogi PM 2029 an anit shti
Daka hero Adel ker from South Africa
hello niharika Kaka rajes ji Meep sain
pratik Shashank baby cheeks Harry anit
gorav uh who else is there Madan Lal Ram
devra Tas dakah hero prush nitin haral
geopolitics Junction m deep Shashank
Harry
gaku shagun tanai soam Chan pram sudhir
pran Rik SG Samar acharia hello random
skull ra Raju chigi chlock curious Prat
J dshit Madan and so on and so forth
everybody hello I will not be able to
greet you all
individually Priyanka aush Harel akat
and so on Welcome All and thank you so
much for being on this live stream so uh
I'm going to take questions that you all
have asked in the comments because
typically in a live stream about science
I've always seen that if I if I do if I
take questions from the live chat uh a
whole bunch of other questions get
introduced like history geopolitics and
whatnot so I'm going to keep it clean
I'm going to take only science questions
from the comments that you all have uh
that you all have asked in the comments
so with that said let us begin with the
questions from the comments
all right pavi okay this is by pramesh
what is Aurora Borealis what is the
significance does it only happen in the
northern regions or anywhere else Aurora
Borealis it's been in the news of late
hasn't it uh there have been these solar
storms uh geomagnetic storms that the
Earth has been facing the brunt off the
past week or so and auroras have been
very visible uh in various parts of the
world auroras were visible from Northern
India from ladak can you imagine that I
haven't heard about such a such An
Occurrence in my living memory Aurora
Aurora visible from India so what is the
Aurora Borealis is it does is it a
phenomenon that only occurs in the
northern
hemisphere not so that's not not quite
the case there is something called the
Aurora Australis as well which is
visible from the southern hemisphere
here from the South Pole region now what
is this phenomenon it's essentially the
Northern Lights the Southern Lights you
see lights shimmering in the atmosphere
it's typically green you also have blue
you also have pink and you also have
various other colors but it's typically
the major color that you typically see
is green so what causes the this this
magical display of shimmering waving
light of various colors it is the
interaction of the Earth the Earth's
magnetic field and the atmosphere with
the solar wind so then we to understand
what the solar wind is the solar wind is
plasma that is emitted by the sun on in
on an ongoing continuous basis the sun
has an atmosphere let's say I mean there
is a there is a region if you go towards
the sun then you will reach a region
where the sun becomes denser than water
but the sun has various layers and one
of the layers can be called the the you
could consider it to be the atmosphere
of the Sun and there are various
phenomena that that exist over there the
sun has a very powerful really really
powerful magnetic field and you can see
the magnetic lines of force in terms of
the solar prominences and all that and
the sun ejects millions of tons of
plasma uh per second I guess and what is
plasma it is essentially bits and pieces
of hydrogen atoms essentially free
protons and electrons that's what solar
wind is that's what the plasma is so all
of this is emitted by the sun in all
directions that's one phenomenon that
happens all the time then you have a
coronal mass ejections which are these
these Loops of matter that come out of
the sun's uh surface and sometimes these
Loops break off depending on the
magnetic field activity and then there's
this massive amount of solar material
that's that's ejected in a certain
direction and if it is coming towards
the Earth then well that causes various
uh phenomena so you have the solar wind
you have coronal mass ejections and you
then you have solar
prominences uh and you have the the
emission of various kinds of radiation
typically very high energy radiation
gamma radiation visible radiation
ultraviolet radiation from the Sun and
so on so now when the solar
wind uh comes towards the Earth then the
Earth itself has a magnetic field which
is way weaker than the sun's magnetic
field and these charged particles
because they are charged they will
interact with the Earth's magnetic field
and and you will see that these
particles generally are dragged or are
pulled by the magnetic field the Earth's
magnetic field towards the polar regions
so this stream this constant stream of
charged particles plasma it converges in
the polar regions because of the
magnetic field of the earth and then it
hits the Earth's atmosphere at various
Heights and various speeds and that's
what causes this this glowing display of
light so when uh this solar wind
interacts with the Earth's atmosphere at
let's say around 300 kilometers above
the surface it will give you a certain
kind of light sometimes it will be blue
depending oxygen at which altitude what
kind of interaction is there that gives
you different colors of light nitrogen
also so I think oxygen at 100 kilometers
above the Earth's surface if it
interacts with with the plasma solar
wind it gives off green light somewhat
higher about 300 km it's it's blue light
and nitrogen gives of various colors and
the same thing the same phenomenon
happens at the South Pole in the South
Pole regions as well but when there is a
massive amount of plasma coming in
because of solar you know uh augmented
solar activity then you may see these
displays of light even at the uh
Southern I mean at at the latitudes that
are closer to the Equator and which is
how we had the recent phenomenon where
we saw auroras from Northern India from
ladak so that essentially is the Aurora
Borealis Aurora Australis it's because
of the interaction of the solar wind
this plasma with the atmosphere of the
earth and it happen it happens near the
polar regions because of the interaction
of this plasma with the Earth's magnetic
field the Earth's magnetic field drags
it and pulls it towards the polar
regions where it starts impacting the
atmosphere of the earth and that's what
causes the phenomenon hope that explains
the matter next
question okay long question question I
am aushi listening to you since age 16
now I'm 19 thank you so much I really
appreciate that
aushi so the question is with
exponential development advancements in
science medical science technology I
wonder we will will we see a future a
time in the future where death will be
optional and will that choice be of
privilege as there is a great shift in
perception of death now it is being
approached more like a technical problem
and discussed seriously among Elites and
scientific communities billions are
being spent on Healthcare and Longevity
with instances of ultra Rich individuals
investing their longevity on their
longevity and doing what not throughout
the ages almost all parities probably
only death has been an equalizer but now
not even that I wonder if we are really
heading towards distopia and that two
not just in one sense do you see it
incoming eager to know your take
okay uh we are in my the way I see it
based on whatever information is
available in the public domain I think
we are very far as as today from making
death optional okay uh I mean people are
doing research biological research on
tiom lengthening and and various other
tase enzymes that will cause t t Tome
lengthening and all that and various
other kinds of research are being done
cognitively also brain wise and and so
on to delay aging to reverse aging and
so on but I think we are way way way far
away from any of that becoming actually
you know controllable and uh actually
delaying death prolonging people's age I
mean what's the average lifespan across
the world I would imagine it'll be
around 75 80 if you can extend that by
even five years that's going to be a
major breakthrough we are nowhere close
to that happening right now the way I
see it in the future you may come you
may there could be advances which could
delay age delay aging and delay death so
let's say you able to add 20 years to a
human being's lifespan through some
treatment through some medical treatment
so a person who would uh typically live
until the age of 80 they will now live
to 100 or maybe you can extend the
average lifespan to
120 even that does not make death
optional you people will eventually die
I mean eventually um the end of life
will happen and uh I don't see any
technology that is currently being
considered or developed or even imagined
that could actually completely take away
the possibility of death because there
are factors that go beyond simply
keeping the body alive okay death is
caused primarily by
aging and uh everything deteriorates and
so on let's say you extend someone's
lifespan and let's say you make it 200
years for example can the human brain
sustain itself for 200 years okay the
human mind because this that's a certain
finite amount of space in which you have
all this data that goes in and it it it
can only
only handle let's say 80 years or 100
years of memories and experiences in
data you go beyond that you're going to
have to start overwriting data and you
may lose old memories and eventually you
may forget who you actually are you may
forget the first 100 Years of your life
if you live to 200 who knows that may
also happen so I don't think that's
something that's desirable
uh so I don't see this sort of dystopia
emerging anytime soon we're going to
have ai we're going to have all these
wonderful advances that are going to
transform uh our life but I don't think
we are at the position even close to it
where death becomes
optional but yes uh if you look at
science fiction writers I mean I I've
read all kinds of Science Fiction from
the 19 from the what 18th century
onwards the first science fiction novel
is is considered to be Frankenstein by
Mary shell and I've read science fiction
for over the ages and if you look at
science fiction written in the 1950s and
60s FR 40s it's very very optimistic and
today all science fiction is pessimistic
it's all dystopian so it looks like
technology is dragging us towards a
dystopian kind of future especially the
big corporations that control technology
and release it and implement it and Al
so and so forth so yeah you could see a
dystopian future emerging but I don't
think death has we are anywhere close to
making death optional right
now okay swapnil says swapnil
Mishra says did SpaceTime have a
boundary at the Big Bang Singularity
given that the universe is believed to
have had zero size at that time what
were the boundary conditions at the
beginning of
time good question did space time have a
have a boundary so we're talking about
the big bang Singularity first of all
the big bang is the event that gave
birth to to the universe that's the best
theory that we have in
cosmology and this big bang event was
not an explosion it was an expansion of
SpaceTime it happened roughly 13.8
billion years ago according to the best
information that we have some people
some researchers would say that it was
it could have been before that maybe
double the time but the mainstream
theory is that it happened 13.8 years
ago and the universe is believed to have
in a vanishingly small point at the time
what we call the big bang Singularity
now what was this big bang Singularity a
singularity from the point perspective
of general relativity is a a position it
is it
is it is a location it's it's it's let's
talk about time you go back far enough
in time in the entire universe the the
curvature of the universe becomes
infinite and the density of the universe
matter and energy dity of the universe
becomes infinite that's your big bang
Singularity now in in mathematics
Singularity when you have a singularity
it essentially means you're dividing
something by zero which is unphysical
and it actually indicates that your
theory is there there is there is some
flaw or deficiency in your
theory so uh maybe there was something
else maybe not a singularity but the
best theory that we have says that there
was a singular Singularity which then
expanded and it it gave rise to the
universe that we have today so uh the
expansion happened in different let's
say stages I mean we look at it from the
perspective of stages but overall it was
just a smooth expansion not entirely
smooth you had inflation which happened
a fraction of a second after the birth
of the universe you had the decoupling
of the forces and all that so uh that's
what happened now what was the geometry
of the universe what was the shape of
the universe what was there something
beyond the universe was there a boundary
between the universe and what is not the
universe we don't know we don't have
sufficient data uh there are these
theories there is a theory put put forth
by Stephen Hawking the late Stephen
Hawking and harle which says that there
was a no
boundary and uh it says that when you go
back closer and closer to the moment of
the big bank then time itself becomes
fuzzy and it takes on spatial Spa the
the aspect of space so there's a theory
like that and so basically what we what
I'm saying is that the physics of the
very early universe is very poorly
understood to properly understand the
physics of the very early Universe let's
say in the first second after the big
bang you would have to develop a quantum
theory of gravity which which
incorporates Quantum effects with
general
relativity
because when the universe was that small
all if all the physics was quantum
physics right because that's the that's
the Ultram microscopic domain the
quantum domain so and and at that point
in time you would have a UNIF unified
force a single Force which then
decoupled and other forces decoupled and
the Symmetry is broke uh and so on so
you would need to develop a a working a
viable quantum theory of gravity which
which uh includes general relativity as
well as quantum mechanics Quantum field
Theory and we don't have that right now
and because of that the physics of the
very early universe is very poorly
understood first of all because we don't
have sufficient data we have data what
data do we have we have the cosmic
microwave background radiation which
came much later on which which was
created you know which emerged out of
the universe out of SpaceTime much later
on so overall we have very little
understanding of what really the
conditions were like at that time and
that's why it is not it is not a a
question that we have a clear answers to
but it is a very fascinating question
and it is questions that like these that
Fascinate physicist and and drive
research forward so yeah there you have
it okay happy faces 228 says what is
space time why space and time are merged
together and how also how can we
perceive time as the fourth dimension
okay what is space time we we understand
the universe we visualize we perceive
the world the universe in three
dimensions length breadth and height
right the three dimensions that's what
we see and we can also perceive the
passage of time our perception of time
is kind of wague and fuzzy but we see
the universe see our life and our the
events that happened around us in a
chronological linear fashion so that is
what gives us the the impression and the
and the and the understanding that time
is passing so time is something we have
a fuzzy understanding of and when it
comes to relativity and quantum
mechanics time is looked upon as a
linear parameter it happens it's a
linear and and in linear Factor linear
parameter in quantum mechanics time is
an external classical parameter it's not
something that emerges out of quantum
mechanics and when it comes to
relativity uh well let's talk about
special relativity first the the easier
part of Relativity there are two kinds
of Relativity special relativity and
general relativity so in special
relativity uh the the uh interval
between two events has the parameters of
distance as well as time okay so you can
see that time as well as distance are
included in the SpaceTime interval in uh
in special
relativity okay and in general
relativity what Einstein did was that he
constructed a
four-dimensional view of the universe in
which we have three dimensions of space
and one dimension of time so it's a
four-dimensional view of the universe a
mathematical view of the universe and
what general relativity tells us okay
the Einstein
equations it's it's a very very
rigorously tested Theory it has
withstood all tests and it is correct so
what it tells us is that there are four
dimensions three of space that we can
see and one of time that we perceive and
time goes linearly well it looks like it
goes linearly and
matter exists in this four-dimensional
stage so whatever happens in the
universe whatever events and uh happen
in the universe they they are played out
on this four-dimensional stage called
space time three dimensions of space and
one dimension of time and every object
every every everything in the universe
every Star every planet every human
being has a world line which which is uh
a path on the four-dimensional stage of
SpaceTime and the presence of matter
curves SpaceTime not just space but also
time all right and the curvature of
space time tells matter how to move so
that's the theory I mean that's the best
I can tell you in words to truly
understand physical theories you have to
look at the mathematical equations but
for that you to understand the
mathematics when it comes to general
relativity you to understand understand
tensor calculus and all that but that's
how one could describe space time so
space and time we see that they are
merged together we see that in special
relativity itself in the SpaceTime
intervals between events so space and
time the these two parameters they come
together in the equations and then in
general relativity it goes in a whole
different uh to a whole different to a
whole different level essentially
happy faces again says uh how can we
imagine the curving of space by Massive
objects so the standard view that that
they will give you is that uh space time
is like a two-dimensional sheet or
Fabric and you put a a ball a ball on
space on on that fabric and the and this
fabric of space time is curved that's
how they'll show it so you are
visualizing some kind of curvature of
space and maybe time also so in two or
maybe three dimensions but here is a
better way of looking at it let me put
this image on the screen check it out so
this is a more three-dimensional view of
how the presence of matter curves
SpaceTime we are actually seeing this in
three dimensions not four dimensions
because the human brain is not able to
visualize is not capable of visualizing
a four
dimensional uh you know Universe we can
only see three dimensions we can't
visualize four
dimensions at least I can't okay I'm not
my brain doesn't isn't that great I can
only see things things in three
dimensions so imagine this was four
dimensional that it would kind of work
like this so that is how you can
visualize or imagine the curving of
space by Massive objects and also how
the curvature of space makes uh bends
the trajectories of these massive
objects the way they move all right
there we are next
okay this is by pratus pratus
R I've always heard stuff like the
physics used in our day-to-day life is
quite different from the physics
observed at the quantum level subatomic
particles follow a mere probability
function phenomena such as quantum
entanglement have been seen where a
single particle can exist in not quite
not quite in two different places it's
not that's not how it works but I'll
come to that what do you think is the
reason for such an enormous difference
in the the physical state of bodies that
coexist in the same universe but have to
follow different laws of physics well
they don't follow different laws of
physics they follow the same laws of
physics but we see the macroscopic world
the Ordinary World that we
inhabit differently and the quantum
effects aren't that Apparent at all in
the in the ordinary mundane world that
we live in but when you zoom in like
hyper zoom in and you will see atoms and
molecules and and subatomic particles
like like protons neutrons electrons and
quarks and whatnot and these particles
they obey the rules of quantum mechanics
so at some stage at some scale at some
scale The Ordinary World that we are
familiar with this Ordinary World
emerges from the quantum scale from the
quantum World okay it does emerge from
the quantum world so how does that
happen yeah that's the question so what
kind of laws do Quantum objects follow
or obey you you have a like you said
entanglement but entanglement doesn't
mean that two a particle is in two
places at once it means a a pair of
particles that are described by the same
wave function can be as far as apart as
far apart as you want maybe a lier maybe
100 light years but certain some of
their properties are are correlated so
if you look at one particle you'll ex
immediately know what is what what is
the corresponding properties what are
the corresponding properties on the in
the other part of the other particle no
matter how far away it is but it doesn't
mean there is faster than light
communication or or any such thing so
that's a little uh difficult to explain
but that's not how it works I'm sure you
watched the some science fiction series
like the three body problem or whatever
in which they're communicating through
entanglement that's not how it works
that that is so wrong that is so wrong
so entanglement means two particles you
could have more but let's say you have
two particles that they they are
described by the same wave function and
some some of their properties are
correlated let's very very silly and
very straightforward uh comparison or
illustration let's say you have a pair
of gloves a pair of gloves okay I have a
pair of gloves one left-handed glove one
right-handed glove I put one in one box
another in one box I I send one pair one
of the gloves to London I send the other
glove to Moscow okay and I myself don't
know which glove is in which box which
one has gone to Moscow which one has
gone to
London now my friends in Moscow and
London the moment they open the box they
will know exactly which box is there in
the other place that's kind of how how a
entanglement works so at the subatomic
level you have entanglement you have
superposition in which particles exist
in in multiple States in a superp
position of multiple states there is the
observer effect the collapse of the wave
function the moment there's a
measurement or an observation the wave
function collapses that is something you
don't see at the at the classical level
at the microscopic level uh there are
all kinds of other phenomena that that
are very uh there is quantization
obviously you know uh there is wave
particle duality so particles can behave
like waves as well as particles the the
electron can behave like a wave it can
also behave like a particle photons
which are massless can behave like
particles as well as waves and so on and
you can you can prove this using
experiment like the double slit
experiment and and all that but such
phenomena are not visible at the
classical level at the the microscopic
level but these macroscopic phenomena
emerge from the quantum from the quantum
level so what happens see for example
and it's because of the the wave it's
because of the wavelength see the
wavelength the the the bo de brly
wavelength of a particle is it
it the smaller the particle is the
larger the wavelength is and the larger
the particle is the smaller the
wavelength is so Quantum phenomena are
are are become apparent and they take
precedence over classical phenomena when
the wavelength is significant
significantly large so photons have
different wavelengths depending the
color of the light this is blue you're
seeing blue photons emerging from this
this fabric here you're seeing orange
photons from behind so the light it
tells you the wavelength kind of if you
know what the wavelength of what color
is and so
on but this ball it also has a the brly
the wavelength but it's extremely small
and that's why the quantum effects are
not apparent and when you I mean you can
even solve the schinger equation for the
Earth Moon system or the sun earth
system and what it will give you is
gigantic quantum numbers principle
quantum numbers and all that and and and
energy levels so the larger the quantum
numbers and the larger the energy levels
the less apparent the the quantum
effects are so uh that's what it is and
then there is the correspondence
principle Neils boher came up with the
correspondence principle which
essentially says that the larger the
quantum numbers and the larger the
energy levels Etc the less apparent the
quantum effects
are so because of that what we have is
that the ordinary mundane macroscopic
World it actually is a Quantum world but
we don't see the quantum effects because
they are not visible enough but there
are certain objects certain certain
phenomena that are purely Quantum at the
macroscopic scale booze Einstein
condensates most of us obviously will
never see them but those are macroscopic
quantum uh objects phenomena macroscopic
Quantum phenomena that's one neutron
stars well we don't really get to see
them but those are quantum objects you
know gigantic nuclei essentially Atomic
nuclei uh then
you have crystals you see this this is
an ordinary quartz crystal it's a
crystalline
object the properties of this Crystal
are purely quantum
mechanical okay the hardness the shape
the angles of at which light light
reflects the colors all of this is
purely quantum mechanical this is a
purely Quantum object this is a
macroscopic molecule essentially so
there are certain Quantum effects that
we see are visible we not may not real
realize it but overall everything that
that exist at the the classical level
the microscopic level emerges from
quantum mechanics from the quantum World
by the correspondence principle all
right happy faces again all right when
do you see quantum computers being
available commercially okay quantum
computers there is a lot of talk about
Quantum Computing the past four five
years I think Google had announced I
mean companies like Google Microsoft
Microsoft and whatever else they are
investing in Quantum Computing they're
developing quantum computers and I think
in 2018 or 2019 Google or somebody
announced that they had achieved Quantum
Supremacy which means that their quantum
computer was able to do a certain task
which a classical computer simply can't
do a standard computer simply can't do
well understand first of all that even
your regular laptops and what all these
computers are based they they operate
based on quantum mechanics
at the at the end of the day those chips
and circuits and the everything that
happens in that it would not happen it
would not work without quantum
mechanical Technologies like
semiconductors and so on the the gates
on a you know on a circuit in a computer
in a regular computer they operate
because of the the semiconducting
property that they have and that's a
Quantum property and all that but
quantum computers are all about uh are
about using quantum mechanical phenomena
and controlling those such as
superposition entanglement and all that
by to by creating cubits Quantum bits
which are superposed bits instead of
classical bits and then you manipulate
those Quantum bits to to perform
calculations and so on that's how
quantum computers work so right now we
are in the early research and
development phase of quantum
Computing I would say that maybe in the
next five or so years five or maybe 10
years you would see hybrid computers
becoming available they'll be very
expensive and only some some
corporations of or governments will be
able to afford them initially so these
hybrid computers will have some some
Quantum component as well as classical
components and they'll be used mainly
for cryptography and for drug Discovery
molecular analysis protein analysis
things like that but those will be
initially hybrid computers because it's
quantum computers uh they they are very
delicate you you need to have an
extremely cold temperature within in
which you create the superpositions and
all those Quantum Computing bits cubits
and cubits are very fragile they need
extremely cold temperatures the the
presence of any heat warmth would
destroy the the superpositions and
entanglements decohere the quantum
effects and then then that's the end of
it and even if it's slightly slightly
warm then you could have errors creeping
into the into the computation you would
need error comp error correct correction
codes and those are still in the process
of development so I think the best
quantum computers right now can
superpose I don't know how many cubits
maybe a handful of cubits maybe a 100 or
so cubits maybe a thousand cubits but
for a proper quantum computer you would
need millions of cubits working together
at the same time uh so I would say five
to 10 years you would have hybrid
systems emerging then between 10 to 20
years you may have a better more robust
more powerful quantum computers coming
but becoming accessible and available to
everybody I mean a Quantum Computing
laptop 20 plus years easily so that's
how I see it happening it's it's a very
new technology it's a nent technology
but yeah it it has very powerful future
applications if you if the technology
can be developed to make it work
properly reliably and
efficiently okay ad Guru Prasad says how
do computer processors understand the
programs or any command Okay computer
processors are called central processing
units now this is a very deep computer
science question I will try and give you
uh an overview so central processing
units right the CPUs these are the
brains of computers and they execute the
instructions and they perform the
calculations that essentially run
programs execute programs and that's
what happens now how does this happen is
the question right so a CPU a central
processing unit has a number of
components there is the Alo the
arithmetic logic unit which performs
arithmetic and logical uh operations
there is the control unit the CU which
decodes which directs operations by
fetching decoding and executing
instructions so fetching instructions
from where from somewhere or from your
hard drive or from a flash drive or
whatever you fetch the instructions you
decode the instructions okay because the
instruction will be written in some high
level language like python or or C++ or
whatever you to break it down you
decompile it to the machine language
level and then you to execute it
sequentially then you so that you have
the Alo you have the control unit then
you have registers in computers which
are which are small and fast storage
locations for temporarily storing data
and instructions okay then you have a
cache which is a very small and fast
memory that stores frequently accessed
data and instructions which essentially
helps to speed up the processing so
that's the basic components of uh of
computers of CPUs now how do CPUs
understand programs and how do they
execute programs so like I said computer
programs are written in high level
languages python C++ and whatever else
it is and they have to be translated
they have to be converted and decompiled
into the machine language which the CPU
can understand and what is machine
language machine language is essentially
binary code binary code ones and zeros
right we've all seen those ones and
zeros but that's what the machines
understand so these high level
instructions have to be decompiled and
converted into the ones and zeros and
then there is the fetch decode execute
cycle that is the cycle by which the
process by which CPUs operate it fetches
uh the control unit of the CPU retrieves
or fetches an instruction from the
computer's memory from the ram it
decodes that it translates the fetched
instruction into signals zeros and ones
which can be understood by the C cpu's
other components then it executes the
instruction it is it is it has already
been decoded and you take it to the
various parts of the CPU let's say you
take it to the ALU the Alo to perform
calculation or
whatever and then there are instructions
that uh is part of the architecture of
the CPU that is the instructions that
the CPU understands and it can execute
every CPU has its own architecture its
uh instruction set architecture which
defines the machine language
instructions and it can understand and
execute so you load a
program uh which is loaded from Storage
let's say you have a game that you want
to run so it's going to be on your hard
drive or you can insert some kind of
storage device and so the program is
loaded into the ram then the CPU uh uses
the program counter to keep track of all
the instructions the next instruction to
fetch it is done sequentially
sequentially in extremely fast uh in
very quick time then the fetched
instruction is placed in the instruction
register it is decoded and it is
decompiled into the ones and zeros then
it is then that it is it will then
signal the ALU and other components of
the computer to perform whatever
operation is has to be performed based
on that instruction that has been
fetched and the results of the operation
are stored somewhere they are typically
stored in a register or they can be
written back to the ram of the computer
and so on so there are addition
instructions there are fetch
instructions that are decode
instructions that are execute
instructions and then you have these
Gates you know logic gates and Gates not
Gates or gates exor gates and whatever
which are all used in various ways to
perform various operations and that is
kind of how it works it's a very very
very high level overview that I've given
it's fascinating computer architecture
computer programming how the computer
works at the very basic low level so
that's how computers work so that's how
computer processors uh they operate by a
combination of fetching instructions
decoding them and executing instructions
in a cycle and this happens over and
over again and the CPUs understand
programs through machine language
instructions which are encoded in the
architecture of the CPU and that's kind
of how it works all right
okay okay dungar Singh Chan says fasting
for how long kills cancer cells in the
body okay so this is not very well
understood we know that there is a
correlation between Cancer and sugar
which is glucose so when you eat sugar
let's say you take you eat a candy or
you eat honey or you eat a chocolate or
you eat a sweet desert that is going to
be broken down in your stomach into
glycogen into glucose okay glucose
essentially the glucose will enter your
bloodstream and then there's the insulin
thing and all that I'll not go into the
insulin M insulin part but the glucose
is a very fast burning very readily
accessible fuel for the cells of the
body so the cells of our body they can
use two kinds of
fuel one is uh glucose and the other is
fat so let's say you are chubby fat
you've got plenty of plenty of body fat
you know then if you don't eat sugar
for let's say four days 5 days then the
body will run out of the sugar reserves
glucose gly glycogen res result and then
it will have to move to burn start
burning
fat and that is a process called
ketosis ketosis and Ketone bodies are
are created out of the breakdown of
lipid cells in your body and uh that is
what serves as the fuel source for the
for your cells so
glucose it is a very explosive it it
athletes need glucose for those
explosive movements like sprinting and
all that if you let's if you look at the
way usan Bolt the world record holder
over 100 meters and 200 meters how he
used to train he would always as part of
the training and and Performance Cycle
he would always take sugar or something
sugary just before a race because that
gives you that explosive burst of energy
which sprinters need if you're a long
distance Runner it doesn't really help
that much because you need to sustain
your run for a long long distance 10
kilometers or if you're Marathon are 30
whatever kilometers in that case fat can
be a more efficient fuel source now the
point is
this um there seems to be relationship
between uh cancer cells and sugar and if
you stop eating sugar or carbohydrates
because that's the same thing
essentially then the body has to go into
ketosis after after let's say three or
four or five days it goes into ketosis
there's no more glucose to burn and that
could essentially possibly starve off
cancer cells and the process of fasting
it is the best best way to enter ketosis
instead of stop instead of you stopping
to eat sugar and carbohydrates and just
focus on protein and fat which could
take time you just stop eating for three
or four days that will that will ensure
that by the day by the time day four is
over your body has entered ketosis and
there are various symptoms that some
people experience some people have keto
flu or whatever what this process does
if you fast for 4 days it is believed it
is I think it's been proven perhaps I'm
not really sure you can look at up that
your immune system regenerates itself
over this 4-day fasting
period and you enter
ketosis and what also happens is a
process called autophagy which means
that all the dead dying ccent damaged
cells in the body are all destroyed and
their spare parts are reused for
creating new cells so if you have
precancerous cells or or maybe even
cancerous cells those could be destroyed
and that's good so that's why fasting
intermittently once once in a while is
is was a good thing but there needs to
be more research I'm not sure if there
has been established a clear link
between fasting and killing cancer cells
but yeah I mean hopefully you don't have
cancer I hopefully nobody has cancer and
uh so fasting regularly maybe once a
week or maybe once a month three four
days that could actually be a great way
to ward off the possibility of Ever
Getting cancer but yeah I think more
research more medical research is needed
to conclusively prove this but yeah it's
been part of Indian tradition fasting
you know either weekly or once in a
month or twice in a month there's always
good reasons for old
traditions okay geopolitical dub asks a
question about physics that's great asop
physics so the question is why is there
no square triangle or other shaped
planet in the
galaxy why is it always Circle or or
spherical round-shaped planets can you
explain the science behind this
yes so it's because of the action of
gravity okay gravity is the weakest of
the four forces what forces do we have
we have the strong nuclear force we have
the weak nuclear force we have the
electromagnetic force and these three
combined to become the electro weak
force and then you have gravity and
gravity is the weakest of the
interactions
okay uh but yeah gravity is what shapes
the universe at the largest scales now
let's say you have a collection of
gas okay and there is an over density
somewhere then because of self-
gravitation this entire gas cloud will
start coaling coaling together it will
start moving together in a certain
direction clockwise anticlockwise in
whichever plane of motion and that is
how Proto Stellar clouds are formed
which lead to the birth of solar systems
with a star at the center okay so it's
because of the action of gravity this
happens now in any Stellar system or
solar system you're going to have some
hard solid material which is going to be
very less compared to the mass of the
star itself but it's going to give rise
to the formation of planets okay and
when you look at
small masses let's say we have asteroids
right these are irregularly shaped why
is that because they are too too small
for Gravity to really take over but when
you have large enough
objects okay with with large large
enough mass then gravity will take over
and it will it will ensure that the most
efficient shape
possible is created and the most
efficient shape possible is going to be
a spherical roughly SP sperical shape
when when it comes to gaseous planets
like Jupiter Saturn and all that they
are mostly smoothly almost spherical not
exactly spherical I come to that in the
case of larger planets like the Earth
and Mars and and and and Venus and so on
I mean they are not as large as the gas
giants much smaller but even here the
gravity the force of gravity has taken
over and uh and broken down the the
various component of Planet into a
roughly spherical shape now because the
planets are rotating there's going to be
an equator IAL bulge and you will see
this more pronouncedly with uh with gas
giants like Saturn and Jupiter even the
Earth itself has an equatorial
equatorial bulge so no not every plan
planet is no planet planet essentially
is perfectly spherical but it's because
of the action of gravity which wants to
create the most efficient shape possible
that this happens so that's why if you
have a planet with the size with the
mass of the earth and you try to make it
into a triangular shape or square square
shape you will see that over time the
the action of gravity is going to turn
that into a spherical shape roughly
spherical shape and the longer the time
goes the more spherical it gets that's
what happens it's because of the the
force of
gravity swapnil Mish says why do we
experience time in a linear fashion in
the universe rather than expon
exponentially or logarithmically
if the universe were to stop expanding
and start Contracting would the
thermodynamic Arrow reverse creating a
decrease in disorder over time and
leading to backward time instead of
forward time okay so why do we
experience time in a linear fashion in
the universe rather than exponentially
or
logarithmically
um experiencing means it is something
that it's it's something to do with our
perception of the universe
now we know that there are certain clear
laws of the
universe we have general relativity we
have quantum mechanics Quantum field
Theory and so on we know that in general
relativity time essentially is a is is
the fourth dimension and in that you can
actually go backward and forward in time
mathematically at least okay when it
comes to Quantum
Mechanics time is an external path
parameter and once again it's a linear
parameter so everything we see about the
universe you see that time is
linear so it's just the way the universe
is and our perception of time is also
linear because we
see events happening
sequentially we experience events
happening sequentially and we have never
experienced events happening backwards
in time so that's just the way it is
that we experience it in a certain
fashion Maybe the universe could be
different and maybe our brains and our
cognition and our abilities cognitive
abilities are not that advanced that we
we would that we could perhaps
experience time differently but yeah the
laws of physics are such that time is
linear maybe in other universes if they
do exist you may have exponential or
logarithmic time but in this universe it
seems to be completely linear now the
other question is also interesting if
the universe were were to stop expanding
and start Contracting would the Third
thermodynamic Arrow reverse causing a
decrease in disorder over time and
leading to backward time instead of
forward time so one of the so time is
one of the biggest mysteries in the
universe what is time what causes time
is time an emerging property of the
universe or is it just an illusion that
we we
perceive well it seems to be connected
with entropy entropy is a measure of
disorder in any system or in the
universe overall the universe is is a
system and it has a certain amount of
disorder
and so any system that has a lot of
disorder Randomness is a high entropy
system and any system that has a very
high amount of orderliness is a low
entropy system I would imagine that uh
some of the lowest entropy systems in
the entire universe would be the human
brains because they are so orderly right
and so full of information and data in a
very very systematic manner stored in a
very systematic manner uh
so what you what you will see is that
according to
thermodynamics entropy of the entropy of
any system increases over time and that
seems to create the uh thermodynamic
Arrow of time because uh in any system
entropy can either stay the same or
increase it can
never
decrease right so that seems to cause
that forward Arrow of time so it seems
to be perhaps
connected to entropy or related to
entropy now let's say like you say the
universe at some point in time because
of it geometry or whatever reason stops
expanding right now the expansion of the
universe is actually accelerating so the
universe is expanding and the
acceleration of the universe is actually
the expansion of the universe is
actually accelerating but let's say in
the future the universe reaches its
maximum expansion point which means that
you have a big crunch situation A
perhaps a cyclical universe or a big
crunch universe and then the universe
starts
Contracting getting back going back
towards the initial Singularity of the
Big Bang okay so what happens then does
it mean that the thermodynamic Arrow
reverses does it mean that the entropy
starts
decreasing well we don't quite know for
sure in in such a situation in such such
a case such a scenario does the entropy
of the universe start decreasing we know
that the volume the size of the universe
will start decre raising but does it
mean that it becomes more orderly over
time and does it mean that the time
starts going
backward I'm not sure that that could
quite be the case because even if you
take a closed system with a gas within
it okay and you squeeze it and you and
you make it smaller you shrink it the
gas will get hotter for sure but will it
become more orderly I don't think so
okay it may actually become more
disorderly
so it may not quite be the case that if
the universe starts Contracting uh it
will become more orderly the entropy
will decrease and the thermodynamic of
Arrow of time will
reverse so yeah but these are all
hypothetical questions we don't quite
know what will happen if this will even
happen or not but very interesting
questions and that these can give rise
to very interesting thought experiments
in physics that can help us unravel some
of the big Mysteries including time
which is one of the biggest
mysteries okay Anway Sharma asks a
similar question the universe is growing
expanding right now and time is moving
in the outward or forward Direction so
when the Big Crunch happens will the
universe coil inwards and will the arrow
of time be reversed I already answered
that and everything that happened in the
past will happen again I don't think
that's quite the case I don't think that
everything will happen in Reverse if the
universe starts Contracting I think its
Evolution will continue in a certain
direction
uh according to the laws of physics I
don't I don't think it will start all
the events will start playing out in
reverse order again I don't think so uh
because the memory of everything that
ever happened might be stored somewhere
in the in the universe uh we don't know
about that whether the memory of
something of everything that ever
happened may be stored somewhere there
is no physical process or law that we
are aware of that would be storing the
memory of everything that ever happened
a record of everything that that ever
happened somewhere you have ol graphy
theory that talks about the surface of
of a sphere of of the universe may may
possibly encode all the information
within but then that where is that un
that information stored outside I mean
that that uh that question isn't
answered when it comes to this
question so I don't think the arrow of
time would be reversed I could be wrong
obviously because we don't know we have
never experienced such a
scenario but uh that's speculation and
hypothetical and according to the laws
of physics as we know them that Arrow of
time will not be reversed what exactly
is information well what is that's a
good question well it depends on the
context in which you're asking me are
you asking me about information from the
context of uh information Theory or from
the perspective of quantum theory from
the perspective of black holes from the
perspective of computer science so if
you if you're talking about computer
science then information is just bits
and bites ones and zeros right like we
discussed some time ago ones and zeros
stored
on the computer's hard drive or in
memory or in Ram or whatever that is
information from the perspective of
uh of computer science from the
perspective of quantum
physics uh information is the various
states of of the system so let's say you
have a system let's say you've got a
square box in which you have a gas
okay let's say you have hydrogen and
helium mixed together
and let's say you have n number of
hydrogen atoms and M number of helium
atoms okay and it's a mixed gas and they
are interacting in somewhere or the
other so in this case information is the
state of each of these
atoms or molecules okay the quantum
States let's take atom one of of
uh of uh hydrogen what Quantum state is
it
in is it in the ground state is it in
the excited state so all of these all of
these various data points taken together
is quantum information are certain atoms
entangled are there superpositions of
some kind and so on so forth all of that
is quantum information uh in information
Theory uh information is correlated with
entropy I'll not go into that it's
pretty complex I don't know how to
explain without mathematics and so on
from the perspective of black hole
physics uh information is again the
quantum states of everything that goes
into the black hole so a black hole is a
classical object okay a black hole is
from the perspective of general
relativity it's a classical object it is
a very simple object from the
perspective of general relativity it has
only three properties Mass charge and
angular momentum and that's it nothing
else so it has a certain amount of mass
it may or may not have a certain amount
of charge and it may be spinning or
rotating or not so Mass charge and
angular momentum and all the properties
of a black hole can be described by the
by using these three parameters these
three
parameters and other properties are
derivatives of these three parameters
for example entropy is a function of the
surface area of the Event Horizon of the
Black Hole uh the radius of the Event
Horizon if it's a shield radius then it
is 2 mg by C
and so on I'll not go into the details
so a black hole from the general
relativity perspective is a very simple
straightforward object but it is let's
say it is black hole that is accreting
gas so it's accreting hydrogen and
helium and what not gas I mean all of
these gas atoms and molecules are
quantum objects and they all have
Quantum information within them it's
also once light crosses the Event
Horizon even light is not cannot escape
the black hole light also has
information polarization in what
direction are the electric and magnetic
fields pointing polarization information
so all of this Quantum information is
going into the black hole it's going
inside right now once it goes inside
where what happens to the information
does it get destroyed it does it get
scrambled and all that that that is the
black hole information
Paradox because black holes of
temperature and they radiate they
radiate the radiation Hawking radiation
which which could be particles
antiparticles it has a black body
spectrum and these particles that are
emitted uh do they encode the
information that went in and so on so
that is the black hole information
Paradox all so it if you want to answer
what is information you have to
understand which from which context from
which perspective you want to understand
computer science black hole physics
quantum mechanics philosophy whatever so
there are lots of different ways of
explaining what information is also
information Theory
okay okay two
questions Smart Buys 3118 says recently
India has successfully tested phase two
the fast breeder stage of thorium
reactors uh how far are we from phase
three and successfully developing it
completely Akash rocks Akash rocks says
uh do you see thorium based power plants
in the near future in India however
scientists cracked the formula to do so
or or do we still have a long way to go
second do you see lithium based electric
vehicles dominating the future do we
have a good amount of lithium reserves
and also reserves of other critic
critical minerals on Earth to support
this change okay so let's talk about the
the thorium angle the the phase two
phase three of the Indian nuclear
program India has successfully tested
one Sodium Reactor the fast breeder
stage thorium reactor how far are we uh
from entering phase three developing
successfully and what is the future of
thorium based power plants in India so
India as I'm sure most people would know
hopefully that India has a three-stage
nuclear power program India has a
three-stage nuclear power program this
was which was developed in the 1950s
1960s somewhere around that time by Dr
homi Baba so this program is was
designed it was it was created this plan
was created to efficiently use India's
reserves resources so India has limited
uranium resources India has to import
uranium from from other countries but
India has abundant thorium resources
reserves India has the highest amount of
thorium anywhere in the world okay so
considering these factors in mind the
limited amount of uranium that we have
and we to import uranium from outside
and we have so much thorium so then
considering that considering all of this
uh the three stage uh program was
developed so the first stage is the
pressurized heavy water reactors okay so
these reactors use pressurized heavy
water uh and they uh use natural uranium
as fuel so the objective of these
reactors is to generate electricity and
also to produce plutonium plutonium 239
as a byproduct okay so in these
pressurized heavy water reactors there
heavy water which is dyum dioxide no
it's it's d2o dyum so d2o is used as the
moderator and the cool ENT okay so that
is the first stage the pressurized heavy
water reactors so these reactors use
uranium As Natural uranium 238 is the
fuel and some of these uranium atoms
absorb neutrons and they get converted
into plutonium plutonium 239 1 238 plus
1 is 239 and they generate electricity
and also simultaneously generate
plutonium in the spent fuel so that is
the first stage we have those reactors
the second stage is fast breeder
reactors so in fast breeder reactors you
are using a mixed oxide fuel which is a
blend of the plutonium 239 and the
natural uranium so you're not using
simply uranium you you're mixing it with
plutonium 239 and that is the fuel that
you're using in these fast breeder
reactors so the objective of these
reactors is to breed more fuel than you
are consuming and also to generate
electricity so the the fuel is going to
be mixture of uranium and plutonium but
it's going to generate even more PL
plutonium than it consumes and it's
going to generate electricity and in
this in such reactors you using liquid
sodium as the coolant okay so that is a
fast B reactor and that is what has been
tested so India was supposed to have
entered the stage three of this
three-stage program a long time ago but
for whatever reason we are we are now
entering phase two and one of these
reactors has apparently been tested okay
so we are not yet at the at the thorium
stage you understand we are still at the
plutonium stage we are now building fast
breeder reactors that use a mixture of
uranium and plutonium that fuel to
generate more plutonium and also
generate electricity that's where we are
the third stage is where you have
advanced heavy water
reactors and you using thorium to breed
uranium which is fusile and which can be
used as a fuel so it uses what's called
a a closed fuel cycle to efficiently use
thorium as the fuel thorium is not
facile but it can absorb neutrons and it
becomes uranium which is facile so in
the reactor thorium absorbs thorium is
th232 it absorbs neutrons it becomes th
233 then it undergoes a DEC a beta dek
and it subsequently DEC to uranium 233
and this uranium can be used as a fuel
it can sustain the reactor's operation
and ensure a continuous fuel supply so
that is the three-stage program we are
still at stage two which is not yet the
thorium reactors okay so the deal is
that India has the world's largest
reserves of thorium which makes it very
attractive resource for long-term energy
security for India so this three-stage
program it its objective is to reduce
dependence on imported uranium and to
leverage Dom domestic resources which is
porium and so on and so forth so that is
the deal so that is where we are the the
IND the the first stage has already been
successfully implemented with numerous
pressurized heavy water reactors which
are operational in various parts of
India they're generating electricity
they're also generating plutonium which
is great okay stage two we are entering
stage two now and we have to demonstrate
the viability of the Indian fast breeder
reactor technology okay and then when we
have sufficient number of fast breeded
reactors then will start entering doing
the development of advanced heavy water
reactors
for which can use thorium as the primary
fuel so that is where we are and that's
the deal so I don't know for what reason
the the program is is uh delayed and and
so on but I'm sure we have the means
to get to stage three hopefully soon
enough you need uh funding resources
government support and all that but yeah
could
happen ainash K says in which direction
did the big bang
happen I'll tell you what the big bang
happened right here and wherever you're
sitting or watching it happened there
also because the Big Bang was not an
explosion it was an expansion of
SpaceTime and the entire universe was
squeezed into essentially just a very
tiny infinite simly small point point
which means everything that we see in
the universe all the stars all the
galaxies and what not Galaxy Super
clusters all of that was squeezed to
that little
Point okay so everything came out of
that little point which means that big
big bang happened everywhere it was not
an explosion it was an
expansion so yeah here is where the big
bang happened wherever you are there
there also it happened as simple is
that okay happy faces 228 says how did
Newton discover the law of gravitation
since it's almost impossible to see any
force between small masses very good
question so which when was Newton born
when was he alive you can look it up I
don't remember the dates so here's the
deal when Newton was a student at that
time
certain uh information about the the
movements of planets and and stars was
available some aspects of the laws of
nature were understood for example from
the experiments of Galileo galile in
Italy in Pisa and so on we knew that
there is we knew that gravitation exists
and we knew about the law of inertia we
knew that masses fall at the same speed
and so on so inertia was known the
falling of masses towards you know the
attraction the force of attraction the
gravitational force was kind of known at
least and uh Kepler's laws of planetary
motion were known three laws of
planetary motion uh so Kepler used data
that was acquired by his by by by taob
It is believed that he that taob got
this data from India but anyway that's a
different story so Kepler's three laws
of planetary motion were
known the way planets you know move
around the Sun in elliptical orbits and
the way they move and so on all of that
so this information was available by the
time Newton started thinking about what
became the new in uh law of gravitation
right so it is said maybe it's
apocryphal of whatever that he was
sitting under an apple tree and an apple
fell on his head and then he had this
brilliant flash of inspiration we don't
know if that really happened or not but
what the Insight that Newton got was
that the falling of objects like apples
on the earth is it could be the same it
could be governed by the same laws
that governed the movements of planets
and stars in the skies so Newton came up
with the first unification of forces
okay uh the laws that that governed the
movements of the celestial objects are
the same laws that govern the falling of
objects on Earth and at that time it was
known that the further a light source is
away moves away from you the dimmer it
gets I think everyone knows that but it
follows an inverse Square
law so the intensity is proportional to
the inverse square of the distance
between you and that light source that
was also kind of known so Newton then
applied that to gravitation that maybe
this this the strength of the
gravitational interaction or the force
is proportional to the inverse of the
dist square of the distance between two
objects and that's how it came up with
the famous equation f is equal to g
capital G M1 M2 upon R 2 okay and uh so
it was a flash of inspiration of INSP of
insight and he said that if it is true
then you should be able to develop uh to
to devel to develop the equations of the
Kepler of Kepler's laws of motion
Kepler's laws of planetary motion from
this so he used his theory of flexions
which is now called calculus which he
had somehow
discovered at the time and uh he was
able to uh get the the three laws of
motion cap Laws of Motion from his
theory of gravitation so that's kind of
the manner in which uh the discovery of
the law of gravitation by Newton
happened it was a flash of insight that
they got but it was also based on the
the speculation initially that the same
laws of motion governed the falling of
objects on the earth that governed the
movements of objects in the sky and and
so
on so I guess that's how it Newton was
able to discover the law of gravitation
and then use calculus to prove that this
law of gravitation is the basis for the
capillarian laws of planetary
motion okay purple rose 0301 says how do
celestial bodies stay afloat in space if
space is
empty space is empty so how do Celestial
body stay afloat you're talking about
floating bodies where are they floating
they're floating in something right so
here's the thing they aren't really
floating the the universe is a stage in
which things exist energy exists matter
exists objects exist massive objects
massive massless objects particles all
of this exists on this stage this stage
is a four-dimensional stage called space
timee
and all the uh dynamics of all the
objects the way they move the way they
they are situated with respect to each
other and so on all of that is uh
governed by general relativity and and
which is gravity okay and inertia so
inertia is Newton's first law of motion
any object will keep on moving in a
straight line or will either stay at
rest or keep moving in a straight line
unless it is acted upon by an extra
external Force I think that's roughly
how we could say it so that is the law
of inter Newton's first law of motion
and then you have general relativity
which is the curvature of space time
Mass causes space time to get curved and
the curvature of space time causes Mass
tells Mass how to move and essentially
this is
what is responsible for the various
locations and positions and movements
and
dynamics of celestial objects so they
don't a float somewhere floating in the
air uh they're out there in in space
time essentially they're out there in
space time now is space empty that's
again another question well space is not
really empty it is bathed in the very
faint Afterglow of the first light of
the universe the cosmic microwave
background radiation which is just about
2.7 or so degrees above 0 Kelvin minus
200 something Celsius you can look up do
the conversion okay so space has this
faint Afterglow it is bathed in this
faint after glow the ancient photons the
first light of the in the aftermath of
the Big Bang but then you also have
Quantum fluctuations all over the place
and that's what Quantum field Theory
tells us and that has been proven to be
true so you have Quantum fluctuations
virtual particle antiparticle pairs
being generated and annihilated
spontaneously all the time all over the
place and then you have other things you
have Trace Amounts of hydrogen gas in in
in space so it's not entirely empty it's
not quite a perfect vacuum there's
always something or the other in there
but yeah that essentially is uh the way
it
is okay Arjun sin says what made the
galaxies of different types okay why do
galaxies come in different shapes in
different types like spiral galaxies
elliptical galaxies irregular galaxies
and so on so yeah that's a great
question so galaxies have existed for a
very long time I think the James web
Space Telescope has shown us that the
first galaxies emerged in the first half
a billion years after the big bang which
maybe the first 300 million years after
the big bang uh so yeah that's been a
big surprise so Galaxies have been
around for a very very long time and
galaxies emerge out of the formation of
stars so you have a tremendous amount of
gas okay and that gas acquires a center
of its own through through the process
of self self-gravitation and then it it
starts spiraling and then you have these
star forming regions where new stars are
born and over time this entire thing
becomes a Galaxy and somehow it acquires
a central super massive black hole and
such a Galaxy a Galaxy that forms in
such a process self- gravitation and so
on that typically acquires a spiral
shape with arms okay so the our galaxy
The Milky Way is a great example of a
spiral galaxy and our neighboring Galaxy
Andromeda is also a beautiful spiral
galaxy okay so that's how a spiral
galaxy is formed now these elliptical
galaxies how are they formed typically
elliptical galaxies are formed by the
merger of two or more spiral galaxies or
or other galaxies so when you have a
spiral shape you have two spiral
galaxies that are going to come together
and merge some people would call it a
collision it's actually a merger there's
no real actual physical Collision of
anything there's too much empty space in
a galaxy for anything to to Really
Collide so it's going to be a merger
it's going to be a gravitational dance
of of billions of objects
the Milky Way and Andromeda are going to
merge in this manner in the next five or
so billion years B billion long time we
never going to see them we never going
to see it but when this
happens the two spiral galaxies they you
know they they get distorted they dance
around for a few billion years and
eventually this the entire thing settles
down and it settled settles down in the
in the shape and form of an of an
elliptical
galaxy so elliptical galaxies are
typically formed through the merger of
two or more regular galaxies maybe
spiral galaxies or gal galaxies of any
other kind so that's how elliptical
galaxies are formed what about irregular
galaxies weird shaped galaxies so the
universe is always moving but it moves
over a very long time period billions of
years so when you see an irregular
galaxy it's a Galaxy that has
experienced some kind of massive
gravitational phenomena
that has Disturbed its shape so it's
either two galaxies in the process of
merging together there is there are
these two galaxies called the mice right
the mice you can Google
it or there has been some other kind of
gravitational uh event that has
distorted it out of shape so typically
galaxies when they're first born would
generally be born in having a spiral
shape then when galaxies merge they
become a larger elliptical galaxy and
when galaxies Collide I mean merge or
are in the process of merging and
dancing the tango with with each other
that's when all these arms are distorted
and torn apart and stars are flung in
various directions that's when you have
irregular galaxies so that is
essentially the answer to your
question okay swapnil says how did the
fundamental
forces fundamental principles how did
the fundamental principles and laws of
physics before chemistry and biology
that govern our universe originate
during the big bag
how are these laws of nature and physics
so consistent and persistent appearing
like
controlled
variables yeah the fundamental
principles and laws of physics that
govern our universe and are responsible
for everything we see these laws and
principles originated during the big
bang and the subsequent evolution of the
universe of the cosmos okay so the Big
Bang was when the original what we
believe to be Singularity Big Bang
primordial Singularity experienced
perhaps a spontaneous expansion or
whatever caused it we don't know what
caused it okay so the universe began as
an extremely hot extremely dense Point
approximately 13.8 billion years ago and
then it expanded and as as it expanded
it started Cooling and it underwent a
series of phase
Transformations that set that set the
stage for the formation of the First
Fundamental particles and the formation
of of the of the fundamental forces we
know we know of four forces the strong
nuclear force the weak nuclear force the
electromagnetic force and the
gravitational force so the first second
of the life of the universe itself is a
tremendously long Epoch the first
fractions of a second in that time the
universe was in a very very highly dense
energetic State okay and then you have a
period of cosmic inflation an
exponential superluminal expansion of
the space so this process of inflation
it helped homogenize the universe and
set the initial conditions for the
development of the physical laws that we
know so well now in the early stage
there
was the entire universe was governed by
a single law that's what is believed
okay we don't know a single unified
force a you know super gravity or
whatever you want to call it the grand
unified Force so that is what the
universe was governed by initially that
is what we believe and as the universe
expanded and cooled the Symmetry broke
spontaneously and we eventually got the
four fundamental forces that we observe
today so this spontaneous symmetry
breaking is a key Concept in
understanding how the difference for
different forces and particles emerged
for example you may have heard of the
higs BOS on the higs mechanism which
which explains how various particles
acquire Mass through interactions with
the higs
field so uh that's what is believed to
have happened now the laws of physics
that that we know they are formulated in
the form of mathematical equations and
they describe the regularities and
patterns of the universe they describe
the behavior of the fundamental
components of the
universe we have the Einstein field
equations of general relativity we have
the shinger equation wave mechanics
quantum mechanics these are all based on
various symmetries and conservation
principles so this mathematical
consistency that we observe everywhere
in the universe as far as we can see the
universe the laws of the universe are
the same everywhere and this
mathematical consistency is what ensures
that these laws apply apparently
universally okay so and all of this is
influenced by Symmetry and the
invariance and transformations of
various laws and so on then we have
conservation laws like the law of
conservation of of momentum of energy of
mass which ensures that everything
remains consistent in the universe and
then you have the standard model of
physics that provides a comprehensive
framework for understanding the the
three forces that we kind of understand
the electromagnetic force weak Force the
nuclear strong nuclear force we don't
quite we not quite capable of uh yet
thus far of of fitting gravitation into
the standard model but that's where you
have it okay and then general relativity
takes care of gravitation and all of
this has been experimentally
validated uh the universe seems to be
homogeneous and isotropic on largest
scales which means that the physical
laws should be the same everywhere in
all directions which kind of makes them
appear like they are controlled
variables and we have evidence that
comes in from the cosmic microwave
background radiation the UN which tells
us that the early Universe had a nearly
uniform temperature and density with
perhaps some regions of over densities
and all and all that so it's a it's a
long long long explanation but that's
kind of how it is when the when you ask
very very fundamental questions as to
how did these principles and laws of
physics emerge and originate we don't
quite have the answers for that we need
to to
develop what is seemingly impossible a
grand unified theory a Theory of
Everything the equation that answers all
your all your questions but we still
don't have it so we are still kind of
you know grouping in the dark and
grappling with these questions but these
are the questions that that Fascinate us
and and drive physics theoretical
physics research search
forward Shashank gar says what's the
difference between dark matter and
antimatter okay let's talk about
antimatter first okay what is antimatter
antimatter is a very straightforward
thing it's a type of matter that is
composed of anti particles AN anti-
particle has the same mass as its
regular particle of ordinary matter but
it has the opposite electric charge and
it has the opposite Quantum
properties so it is not just char chared
in an opposite manner positive to
negative but the quantum numbers are
also the quantum properties are are also
the opposite and when a particle and and
its corresponding antiparticle meat they
annihilate and they release a tremendous
amount of O A Very properly measurable
amount of energy in the process so for
example we are familiar with electrons
yes electrons electric shocks so
electrons have antiparticles called
positrons so theit Ron has the same mass
as the electron but instead of a
negative charge it has a positive charge
so that's a positron that's the anti
particle of the electron now we know of
protons protons are positively charged
they are components of of the nuclei
right so the proton has an anti particle
called the
antiproton so the antiproton has the
exact same mass as a proton but it has a
negative charge the neutron is also a
component of the nuclei of various atoms
apart from hydrogen so the neutron as we
know is a neutrally charged particle it
has no real charge no charge even the
neutron has an anti- particle called the
anti- neutron which once again is elect
electrically Neutron but it has the
opposite Baron number okay then
neutrinos have corresponding anti
neutros with opposite lepton numbers so
like I said when particles and
antiparticles come together in the meat
they annihilate each other in a burst of
energy typically photons and these are
typically high energy photons gamma rays
and and it could be also particle
antiparticle
pairs uh so yeah that's how it goes and
anti antimatter can be produced in
particle colliders like the large hydr
collider particle collisions and
accelerators and also in certain types
of radioactive decay
spontaneously and yeah that's what
antimatter is now what is dark matter
dark matter is nothing it has nothing to
do with antimatter it is the mysterious
25% or so of the universe that we don't
understand if you look at the total mass
energy composition of the universe we
see a lot of stuff out there in the
universe don't we we see stars galaxies
nebula nebulas quazars pulsars neutron
stars whatever all that you add all of
that together all of that matter
together in the universe that makes up
only 4% of the mass of the universe 4%
that's it the rest of the universe is
unknown it is dark we only understand 4%
of the universe and that too not very
well okay so then there is about 25 or
so percent roughly which is dark matter
and the rest about 70 71% maybe 69% is
dark energy which is even more
mysterious I'll not go into that dark
energy because you didn't ask me about
that so what's dark matter dark matter
is most likely some kind of particle or
particles which interact only
gravitationally some physicists will say
that dark matter can have the weak
interaction well that for me that's not
dark matter because we can detect
neutros I know that most of them pass
through us there are trillions of solar
neutros that are passing through my body
right now every
second and they typically don't interact
at all with the ordinary matter but yes
we can still detect neutros which means
that they are not dark
matter from my perspective dark matter
has to be purely gravitating matter some
weird kind of particle that we are not
familiar with or family of particles or
class of particles so it's quite likely
there is dark matter in this room with
me and it may be passing through me
right now and it will interact even more
weakly than than uh neutrinos way more
weakly than neutros or it is essentially
impossible to detect but we can detect
its presence through gravitational
lensing and the Dark Matter Hallows that
are known to exist around around
galaxies and so on so it is some kind of
matter that we don't know that we are
unable to understand probably some kind
of particle or particles maybe it has
something to do with primordial black
holes or microscopic black holes or
perhaps bound States stable bound states
of microscopic black holes Quantum bound
States perhaps who knows so yeah that's
the difference between dark matter and
anty matter
Anway Sharma says what are
tons well well well well well you remind
me of ECG Sudan the great great
physicist who should have got at least
three double prizes but he got none we
not go into that story but I think it I
believe it is he who first put forth the
proposal of
tons so tons are a hypothetical class of
particles that travel faster than light
and you cannot bring them down to light
speed or below light speed they only
travel faster than light which means
they have imaginary Mass their mass is
imaginary okay uh you can calculate that
using the basic equations of uh special
relativity I'll not show the calculation
because we are just talking here so a
tachon a particle that can only travel
faster than light would have an
imaginary Mass what's an imaginary
number it's a it's a number that
involves I the square root of minus one
okay so that essentially is what tacons
are imaginary mass and and they the if
if tons exist you would have causes
before
effects and that's why it looks like
they don't exist but who knows so yeah
that is in brief what tons
are okay akad says if the observable
universe is 90 billion light years wide
in D in
diameter how come it's just 13.8 billion
years old is good question yes there is
something called The Cosmic horizon or
the observable
universe and if the universe is 13.8
billion years old as all the best data
tells us then the fast the furthest that
a light that a light Ray can travel
should be 13.8 billion light years
correct right but we observe light
coming from about 45 billion light years
away that that tells you that the radius
of the observable observable universe is
about 90 billion light years but it
should just be the radius should just be
13.8 billion light years why is it so
that it is actually much larger than
that well the answer is very simple it's
because of uh the expansion of the
universe the very fabric of SpaceTime is
expanding and what's causing the
expansion we don't quite know maybe it's
dark energy that is doing it but because
the universe has been EXP
expanding that's why we see light coming
from so far so far away even though it
is just at most 13.8 billion years old
and how do we know that it has expanded
that much because that light is red
shifted we see the light being red
shifted we know the characteristic
spectral lines in various of the various
elements and you see the same spectral
lines but they are shifted towards the
red end of the spectrum that's red shift
which tells you that the light has come
from it has it has had to travel so much
more because the source is moving away
from you it's the Doppler effect
essentially if you have blue shift as in
the case of light coming from the
Andromeda galaxy then those spectral
lines will be shifted towards the blue
end of the Spectrum which means that it
is coming towards you and all the
wavelengths are squashed frequencies are
sorry frequencies are squashed together
and that's why the frequencies are
higher blue shifted so that's how we
know that uh all this Ancient Light
that's coming towards us is red shifted
highly red shifted some of it is totally
infrared and that's why we have to use
instruments such as the James web Space
Telescope that is something that only
detects infrared wavelengths because
they are so so tremendously red shifted
that they are no longer visible so yeah
that's why the observable universes is
90 billion light years in diameter even
though it's just 13.8 billion light
billion years old it's because of the
expansion of the universe which is
accelerating okay B babo pradan says if
our universe expansion accelerates if
the
universe if its expansion is
accelerating so how does our universe
get an external Force to accelerate well
we don't know what it is that's causing
the expansion that's that's a good
question a very straightforward solution
to this to this problem is that somebody
from outside the universe is is
imparting some external Force which is
causing the universe to to to expansion
to accelerate so maybe the universe is
like a balloon
this is a tennis ball but like a balloon
and somebody from outside has this uh
you know this pump and they're pumping
in more air and that's why expanding
well that that's a very straightforward
it's called the ex makina in infection
you know a a plot device that that
solves any problem it's God or it's some
aliens from outside who are providing
energy to the universe to make it expand
and make and accelerate the expansion
when well that that sort of solution can
solve any problem that you have but we
want to look for a mathematically and
physically logical and consistent
solution this problem so it could be
what we call dark energy which makes
about makes up about 70% of the mass
energy of the universe then we don't
know what it is is it a fluid is it a
force what exactly is it it seems to
permeate everything it should be here
but it's completely unknown and May
maybe it is that that is uh footing the
bill of the the energy bill of the
expansion of the universe so yeah we
don't have the answer but maybe the the
answer May lie in the solution to the
mystery of what dark energy
is okay aragi says please explain
Hawking radiation and how will black
hole van after trillion trillion
trillion trillion of years yeah black
holes are weird objects I wish I had a
black hole in a lab then I would really
be able to you
know get get data new data that could
help throw light on what gravity
actually is like at the quantum scale
but we know that black holes most likely
exist we have seen objects that look
like black holes we know that there's a
black hole at the center of the Milky
Way we know there's a black hole at the
center of this of of
U uh whatever other Galaxy we we
recently took a snapshot of the The
Event Horizon telescope so we know black
holes exist they have been
observed
now what we find what what Stephen
Hawking demonstrated using a semil
classical
calculation is that black holes actually
evaporate okay they lose Mass so we know
that a black hole has an EV Horizon and
anything that that crosses that Horizon
will never be able to return from the
black ho it will eventually fall inwards
towards what's believed to be the
central Singularity of of the black hole
and as you fall inside you get all
distorted Twisted out and the
spaghettification happens and not a good
way to go unless it's it's a gigantic
black hole so uh that's what you have
but now at the boundary of the black
hole at the boundary of the uh Event
Horizon we I I referred to some time ago
about the uh Quantum field Theory effect
of the spontaneous creation and
annihilation of particle anti partical
Pairs and that is something that kind of
kind of violates the Heisenberg un
uncertainty principle but the particle
anti particle pair again spontaneously
uh annihilates itself before the delta T
condition is violated in the uncertainty
principle so it's fine okay so let's say
you have particle anti particle Fair
pair that is formed right at the right
inside the Event Horizon boundary and
this anti particle particle pair is it's
formed like this and one particle Falls
inside the Event Horizon can never come
back and the other one goes in the other
direction so essentially the black hole
through its gravitational field is
footing the build the bill the energy
bill of creating this particle
antiparticle pair this virtual pair
which was supposed to spontaneously
annihilate itself and and then no energy
would have been lost but what happened
is that one particle escaped and one was
absorbed which means means that the
black hole is actually lost Mass the
particle that fell inside is considered
to have negative mass and the particle
that goes out is considered to have
positive part positive Mass so if you're
an observer at a distance it will look
to you it will look like the black hole
is radiating radiation is coming out of
it because of this effect and this is
called Hawking radiation so this tells
you that the black holes have
temperature because radiation is coming
out it is black body radiation okay
completely random radiation that's
coming out of black holes so black holes
have a temperature and the temperature
depends on the inverse of the mass of
the black hole inverse of the square of
the mass of the black hole of the mass
look it up look it up okay uh so that
tells you that the larger a black hole
the colder it is and the smaller a black
hole the hotter it is which and if it is
hotter it means it will radiate faster
so the hotter a black hole it is the
faster it radiates and it eventually
ends up exploding boom it's so black
holes end their lives in explosions but
when it comes to large black holes super
massive black holes they are so cool
that they are
cooler than than the interstellar space
the they are colder than the cosmic
microwave background radiation
temperature which means they accreate
over time which means they are
essentially Immortal they will never die
their lifetime is longer than the
current age of the
universe so yeah that is what Hawking
radiation is and that's why some black
holes are apparently Immortal their
their lifetime is apparently longer not
apparently you can calculate and
demonstrate it's longer than the current
age of the universe they're going to be
around essentially forever from for all
intents and purposes so yeah trillions
of years possibly there you have
it okay an Sharma says whenever an event
happens or time passes a part of the
information is either stored in our
memory or in some other digital format
okay so is it possible to reconstruct
the entire event or thing because it
exists but in our conscious memory and
not in the external world you see our
memory is fallible and it is not
perfect unless you are one of those
super Geniuses who have a photographic
memory but most people our memory is is
very it's vague it's imperfect we have
Recollections that are not entirely
accurate and the longer the event longer
ago the event happened the fuzzier our
memory is okay and let's say I observe
this ball bouncing and up up and down
but do I know the exact composition of
the ball every single molecule every
single Quantum State how what is the air
pressure inside how many air molecules
are there inside what is the oxygen
nitrogen carbon dioxide helium Etc
composition of the gas inside the ball I
have no idea so how do you reconstruct
the whole thing from just my vague
memory of the ball bouncing around so
that's why it is not possible to do that
okay the human brain brain is is
marvelous but it's a very small object
and it simply cannot contain the entire
record of what happens forget about the
entire universe in our V our own
vicinity I don't know what's happening
behind me right now maybe there's some
there's a fly or a mosquito flying
around I don't know right so there you
have it so lots of OB lots of events
happen without any conscious Observer
observing them so so you cannot
reconstruct all these events all
right okay swapnil says what triggered
the Cambrian explosion during the
Paleozoic Era in which there was an
explosion of animal life where did all
this new genetic information come from
in a geological instant so the Cambrian
explosion happened about 500 million
years or so ago 540 roughly half a
billion years before today until that
time the entire world the entire you
know uh landscape of life was very
straightforward multicellular and
unicellular life forms but the camaran
explosion was this tremendous you know
creative outpouring of genetic
experiments and it's the first time you
have in the fossil record animals with
hard shells and exoskeletons and
endoskeletons uh so what caused it we
don't quite know what caused it maybe
there was an abundance of oxygen see
initially in the initial phase of the in
the first phase of life on the planet
oxygen was a poison and there was this
great oxygenation catastrophe that
killed off about 90% plus of all life
forms on the planet that is there is
that is more than three billion years
before today or roughly around three
billion years before before today but
later on oxygen became the the gas that
life forms need to stay alive to survive
even today for us if you breathe in too
much oxygen or pure oxygen for a long
time it kind of acts like a poison and
it's not a good thing but yeah so around
540 million years before today maybe
there was an increase in the oxy
oxygenation level of the atmosphere
maybe an increase increase in the oxy
concentration of the oceans as well and
maybe that caused this certain
outpouring of of uh of so many new kinds
of of of uh species maybe the the the
amount of calcium and and phosphate and
all that in the oceans also increased
which gave which enabled animals to
develop endoskeletons exoskeletons and
all that so uh that's what the fossil
record tells us we have the burges Shale
in in England in the British islands and
so on so we see this certain outpouring
of genetic diversity and maybe uh maybe
it's the first time pred Predators
predatory animals emerged in the oceans
which necessitated that other animals
also had to uh evolve and take
evolutionary defense defensive measures
and and evolve in such a way that the
Predators could not catch them very
easily and and devour them very easily
so so maybe that also was uh one of the
causes of so much diversity uh emerging
but all those animals that emerg at the
time they are the ancestors of all the
animals that exist today and one of them
fely was our ancestor as
well
yeah okay Danos says thoughts on
manipulating tilers to extend human
lifespan is it a viable option is it
ethical to do so so in our cells you
have chromosomes and at the end of
chromosomes you have tilers okay these
are genetic ends of the chromosomes and
as cells multiply over and over again
the Tome get shorter and shorter and
that is the the the phenomenon that is
associated with the aging process so the
shorter your tilers are the older you
are and the more visibly aged you are
wrinkles and whatnot okay all that so
that's the aging process so it is
believed that if you reverse this and if
you lengthen the T tome in yourselves
again that you may get youthful and you
may either stop the aging process or
even reverse the aging process and there
is an enzyme enzyme called tilas that is
that is believed to be that is known to
uh cause the lengthening of tilers but
there are risks involved in that because
if you lengthen ters it can very
strongly give rise to cancerous
cells Immortal cells that simply don't
want to die cancerous cells don't die by
the way uh unless the host dies but you
may have heard of the Henrietta lack LAX
uh cell line which is
Immortal if you want to look into that
so one of the risk factors is cancer you
play around with with Tas and and
extending the length of tome you may end
up causing cancer but yes that is
something that is this this
technology of uh of lengthening not
technology but resch search into this
matter Tes and and lengthening T is
going on right now and maybe it could
give give rise to interesting
developments and maybe you know people
could have longer lifespans as as a
consequence of that it certainly is
viable we I think in the infancy of such
research is it
ethical I don't think there's any human
rights concerns or anything the only
only risk is that you may end up giving
people cancer so you have to be really
careful about that these is uh we know
how things have been in medical science
so we need to be a little more careful
so as long as you do it properly and do
your due diligence then it's reasonably
ethical to do
so swapel says why do singled digit
numbers go up to only
nine why is 10 a two-digit number and
cannot be written in a single digigit
format moreover why are numbers 0 to 9
shaped and written the way they are okay
the shape thing is a historical thing it
all came from from the Indian numerals
brahi and all that so we'll not talk
about that that today the reason it's
shaped like that is is because these are
Indian numerals that were uh adopted by
the Arabs then transmitted to Europe
that's how it happened now why do single
digit numbers go up to only nine it's
because we use the decimal system base
10 base 10 which is why we have only 10
characters 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 that's 10
characters and then if you want to go
beyond that you need to use two digits
we have the base two system the binary
system in which you have ones and zeros
only so that in that numbers become long
very
rapidly then you have other systems like
the hexa decimal system which is base 16
in which you have the digits 0 to 9 and
then you have a b CDE e
f a b CDE e
f g okay I don't remember right now but
yeah so that's the hexad decimal system
then you have something called the
vigi vimal system I think vigesimal viml
system which is base 20 in which you
have 20 characters so until you reach 20
you will have a single digit format so
it entirely depends on what base you're
using to to write your numbers base two
which is decimal base two which is which
is binary base 10 which is decimal base
16 which is hexadecimal base 20 which is
vml or whatever okay that's how it is
it's just the way you which Bas you
use okay indrajit says what are your
thoughts on the primordial black holes
some papers say that these are micro
black holes and they are responsible for
Dark Matter also I wonder how matter was
compressed below the schwas radius to
form them if they exist or is there some
other way so primordial black holes are
supposed to are are believed to be those
microscopic black holes that were born
per perhaps in very large numbers in the
very very early Universe in the infancy
of the universe when the universe was so
so small and so squeezed together that a
very small Quantum fluctuation would
create a region of uh of of matter over
density in which the matter was
compressed Beyond its fossil radius and
maybe there was an over
production of micro black holes at
various epochs in the very early
Universe during the pre-inflation phase
maybe during the inflation phase maybe
during the reheating phase recombination
phase whatever okay there are several
scenarios that that point towards a
possible over production of primordial
black holes in the very early Universe
in the various early stages of the
universe's existence so that's a
mechanism by which primordial black
holes could have formed okay
now we know that the early Universe was
very hot and plod black holes were in
this soup of radiation which means they
could have possibly accreted matter over
time and then the universe expanded
became cooler and then the primordial
black holes would have started radiating
because they became hotter than the the
environment and as we know like we
discussed hooking radiation every black
hole is a temperature the small the
smaller it is the hotter it gets and so
on uh so it's possible that some of
those black holes born in the very early
stages of the universe may still exist
today if they were born with a certain
kind of amount of
mass
um if that is the case then we should be
able to detect them we should be able to
detect the end stage
explosions of primordial black holes but
we have never seen that we can detect
gamma ray bursts we can detect other
things cosmic rays and so on but we have
never detected what what seems to
be an exploding primordial black hole
why is that it does it mean that
primordial black holes never existed
does it mean that they all evaporated
long time ago or does it mean that they
are
still tied up somewhere else in some
form yeah so that's my thoughts about
primordial black holes uh they could be
responsible for dark matter as a
component of dark
matter um and so
on maybe if they formed stable bound
States gravitational bound States in
which they don't Decay don't evaporate
then they could perhaps uh form be a
component of Dark Matter there is also
the the possibility that U um once it
evaporates enough there's there's a
plank plank Mass sized particle that's
left behind which is either called a
plon or a coruc copion or whatever which
doesn't Decay which is stable so that's
one possibility that that once a black
hole primordial black hole evaporates
out and it reaches the plank mass then
it cannot evaporate any further and then
you have these Remnant remnants
incredible amounts of plank Mass sized
remnants of primordial black holes which
cannot evaporate any any further and
which are p poorely gravitating objects
that could certainly be a
viable uh form of dark matter if that
exists but do they exist we don't know
because it's very hard to detect them
almost impossible using current
technology so there you have
it Dominic
says is it possible to make a spacecraft
which can use the plentiful hydrogen
available in out
space so in outer space in the vacuum in
the so supposed vacuum of outer space
you have race amounts of hydrogen you
have antiprotons protons electrons all
of that roaming around but in in a very
dilute form so is it possible to make a
spacecraft that can utilize this
hydrogen that's out there all this
hydrogen well theoretically it's very
much possible theoretically it's called
a bassard Ramjet which will have a
gigantic Ram scoop which is made up of
these massive magnetic fields which
Scoops in hydrogen
in front of the spacecraft over over
area of multiple liers which means the
are gigantic Ram Scopes okay if it is a
circular thing it's it's like multiple
liers in in area and then that sucks in
all this hydrogen and that serves as the
fuel for the Ramjet that drives the
spacecraft forward so that's a concept
called a bassard Ramjet bu SS a r d b
dram jet so yeah theoretically very much
possible but technologically Is it
feasible for us to do that I think we'll
have to become a type 1 civilization or
something before
that okay ratna says ratna Singh says uh
please throw some light on asteroid
Mining and interplanetary human species
in the future okay so we are not quite
an interplanetary species right now no
human being has ever set foot on another
planet the furthest we gone is the moon
which is our own
satellite um we have human beings in
orbit around the Earth on the
International Space Station and various
Nations have the ability to send human
beings into space the Chinese have it
the Indians will also do it in a year or
two by 2026 or something so uh that's
the best we can do right now the best we
can do technologically is to get to the
moon now maybe by 2030s by the 2030s
maybe by the 2040s you may have the
first human beings on Mars that's what
Elon Musk wants to do the technological
ability to do that will be available to
him very soon that gigantic rocket is
developing so uh so yeah eventually we
if all goes well we will become an
interplanetary spaes the next place we
will go to will obviously be Mars which
is the most logical place to go to Venus
is too hot too hellish to even think
about unless you want to stay in orbit
or in the upper reach of the atmosphere
of Venus but Mars makes sense it is
smaller it is more earthlike and you
could even terraform it over a period of
a few centuries or or faster if you use
dirty means and so on so yeah Humanity
could become an interplanetary species
in the future as long as we do things
properly and don't have a third world
war or whatever asteroid mining is is
much more far-fetched theoretically
certainly you can do it you get
asteroids which are rich in various
metals and minerals you know some
asteroids may have more more iron than
the entire
iron uh or that's that's present on our
planet that's also possible but the
thing is this the asteroid belt between
the orbit of Mars and and Jupiter it is
almost empty okay it's a tremendously
large number of asteroids but it's
almost empty space there are millions of
kilometers between two asteroids on
average it's almost empty space so how
do you find the asteroids how do you
reach there how do you mine them how do
you bring them back to your planet it's
a tremendous amount of investment of
time of of of resources of fuel and all
that that you have to do just to get the
contents of one asteroid back So
eventually if you if you have have the
technology to harness the resource of of
the whole solar system then asteroid
mining makes sense but right now it's
it's it's far-fetched it's not going to
create trillionaires billionaires
anytime soon at least not for the next
Century minimum maybe not the next
couple of centuries I could be wrong I
hope I'm wrong but the way the
technological progress is happening it
doesn't look like that that that's going
to happen so uh theoretically very
possible but practically impractical
from a realistic
perspective ad Guru Prasad says uh
artificial rain
okay Is it artificial rain or something
else that was responsible for the Dubai
floods it was cloud seeding it was
artificial rain that caused the Dubai
floods because of a free combination of
weather conditions so what is artificial
rain how is it created what is cloud
seeding cloud seeding is when um you
create artificial rainfall for whatever
Reasons by seeding the air above a
region with
nucleation with with particles that act
as nucle ation points for the creation
of water droplets or ice droplets which
could eventually become snow or or or
rain so you typically use sodium
iodide or sodium chloride or or some I
think I can remember sodium I iodide
silver iodide and sodium chloride these
two and you release fine grains of these
spine particles of these and these are
seated in the atmosphere here in the air
and they act as nucleation points for
cre for the creation of water droplets
clouds and all that and then it gives
rise to rain so that's how cloud seeding
happens and that's how artificial drain
is created now if you go to the UAE and
all in that part of the world you will
see that there's a lot of artificial
clouds being created if you are flying
over the the Arabian peninsula in the
UAE region you'll see this weird cotton
like clouds that are that are all spaced
out almost in an even
spacing okay and very close to the
ground it's so strange it's very
unnatural so these are artificially
created clouds and these clouds give
give rise to rainfall that uh that is
good for them overall because they would
like more Greenery and more better
cooler temperatures and all that but
then what happens is sometimes you you
have a situation in which various air
currents come together and all these
clouds they are not able to go out and
the
atmospheric water doesn't disperse and
that is what can give rise to these
freak conditions that give that create
torrential rainfall and that's what
happened in Dubai recently so this very
dry desert area very arid Place suddenly
had tremendous rainfall and flooding
unheard of so that happened because of
cloud seeding and artificial rainfall
and I think even Oman had to Bear the
brunt of this uh of this
flooding okay so I have exhausted the 28
or 29 or 30
questions roughly 30 questions that I
had picked let me now take a couple of
minutes and maybe take some questions
from the live chat in case you have any
questions okay let's see this question
sarvagya Sharma says if a wormhole was
to open and and everyone on earth goes
to a different Universe with entirely
different laws of physics then would we
notice the difference or will be will
thinking process change
I think if we are we we are sucked into
a wormhole and transported to a
different Universe where you have
different laws of physics then we will
not function the way we are supposed to
function and that would essentially mean
the death of
us I'm not even sure whether it's
possible
to travel through a wormhole
unscathed okay wormholes may not be
traversable in some cases you would need
some exotic matter in the throat of the
Wormhole to make it traversible exotic
matter such as matter with negative Mass
ooh imagine that or you may need cosmic
strings primordial cosmic strings to
keep the throat of the Wormhole open but
the conditions in the throat could be
horrifying for life I mean not not
amenable to the survival of human beings
unless you are in a in a very strong
spacecraft but then you end up let's say
like you're saying in a different
Universe well you won survive that but
Wormhole
wormholes from the general relativity
perspective worm holes don't take you to
a different Universe they they take you
to a different location in the same
universe but yeah there you have
it
okay okay Karan alaat says what is
quantum cosmology so we know what
cosmology is it is about the evolution
of the universe the cosmos astrophysics
is more to do with the various objects
that exist in the cosmos like nebula and
pulsar and quazar and neutron stars and
stars and galaxies and so on cosmology
is about the evolution of the universe
large scale evolution of the universe
and all that so Quantum cosmology is
about using quantum mechanics to explain
the evolution of the universe that's
very simple straightforward and very
brief answer to your
[Music]
question okay see this is the problem
this is why I don't take questions from
the live chat when it comes to science
because you will have all qu you will
have questions about other other topics
in
there
okay um
okay here we are Tushar Verma says what
are white holes white holes are you can
think of see we have the Einstein field
equations of quantum of general
relativity okay and we have various
solutions to these Einstein field
equations so we have the black hole
solution we have the Wormhole solution
and then we have white hole solution so
what are white holes you can think of it
this way you know what black holes are
we all know what black holes are like
people think of black holes as this
giant vacuum cleaners that suck
everything inside that's not quite the
case a black black hole is just an
object which cannot radiate light
because the mass is contained within the
schwat radius of the Event Horizon all
of it so that's why it is completely
black or transparent black actually
black they're like holes in SpaceTime
now imagine a Time reversed black hole
so a black hole whatever comes in its
way it will suck it in right it'll suck
it in if if something is coming towards
it even eventually it will end up inside
the black hole so it's from that
perspective it's like a vacuum cleaner
now imagine a black hole with time
reversal so time is Flowing backwards
then you will see the black hole
throwing out stuff outside right instead
of swallowing it will be vomiting stuff
regurgitating stuff so that's
essentially what a white hole is it is
like a Time reversed black
hole and when it comes to the objects at
the center of galaxies we don't know
whether they are black black holes or
white holes I mean you
know so there are certain tests that one
could do to try and figure out whether
it's a black hole or white hole but
that's what it is so a black hole a
white hole is a specific solution of the
Einstein field equations and it's like a
Time reversed black
hole okay I already took the question
about
antimatter uh what else do we
have tripped reverber
River bur what's the difference between
radio wave signals and Laser signals and
how laser signals will be more effective
for future communications uh radio
signals are
modulated are modulated uh
electromagnetic waves at a certain kind
of at a certain range of
frequencies uh so they are
electromagnetic waves for sure okay and
they exist they are at a certain range
of frequencies and there's modulation
time modulation frequency modulation all
of that uh I'll not go into the details
of that but you can look up those
concept Concepts if you like so those
are radio signals certain a certain
specific range of frequencies laser what
is a laser the the full form of L is
light amplification by
stimulated emission of
radiation okay so one of the so when
Einstein developed the the the quantum
theory in the early 20th century needs
boher came up with the quantum atom the
boher model of the atom that was refined
later with wave mechanics and the and
Matrix mechanics and so on and so forth
then Einstein came up with a new form of
new means of of quantum jumps a new kind
of Quantum
Jumping in atomic orbit in in atoms
electrons going from you know one Atomic
level to energy level to another and
that is stimulated emission of photons
so you shine a light of a certain
frequency on the atom and and that atom
will emit light of a certain frequency
and you can uh stimulate it essentially
so if you have a gas let's say argon
Neon gas and you do the you do this
process and it can then it can emit
very cated
light and light that is in Phase so that
light doesn't you know
diverge out or diffuse out it stays
laser focus laser sharp that's why say
we say laser sharp so that essentially
is laser signals uh are laser signals
more effective for future communications
I'm not sure about that I've not thought
about it um
maybe maybe they could but lasers are
great for focusing energy in a very
small beam of light so you can use
lasers for other things like taking down
drones and missiles and all that you
know once you have enough energy and
yeah that's what is being used these
days to take down as as anti-missile
defense okay let us take one more
question now come on man not this okay
let's take this I was about to take this
one are chupacabras real I've seen no
evidence of them
chupacabras okay so there's the question
Shin
Pama do you think in will again lose the
race to moon in claiming territory as
USA China possibly Russia will land
their people first in the moon and claim
territory the us is going to land people
on the moon in the next year or two by
26 I believe the first moon landings
return Landings will begin as far as I
know the Chinese want to have people on
the Moon by the 2030s the Russians also
have Ambitions of that India says we
will send up Chandra and 10 or 12 or
whatever to the Moon by 2040 with human
beings so look
first Mo Advantage isn't that big as it
is made out to be uh it is obviously a
competition it's a race and all that uh
but I think uh claiming territory and
and all that will happen once you have
sufficient people on the moon which
which uh may not need a very significant
first mover
Advantage
okay
um shall we take maybe one more question
question okay om beerer has asked can
future events affect the present what is
the delayed Choice Quantum eraser
experiment if I explain that at this
point in time it will take me at least
10 to 15 minutes so I will not explain
that but it is an experiment that kind
of seems to hint at
retrocausality
retrocausality which means a future
event affecting the
present means whatever is happening in
the present is affected by what's going
to happen in the future that's so weird
it's called r causality and the delayed
Choice Quantum eraser experiment kind of
hints at that but maybe it's not quite
the case maybe if you investigate it
properly it may not turn out to be
retrocausality so as far as we know the
Quant delayed Choice Quantum eraser
experiment seems to hint at retro
causality future EV events affecting the
present but maybe if you look
investigate properly it may not be the
case okay I not explain the experiment
right now because it will take too much
time but yeah great question okay I
think we are at the end of today's
session 2 hours 6 minutes and whatever
seconds so yeah I'm going to end it over
here so great to do science physics
cosmology all that once again I'm going
to keep on doing
this more frequently more regularly so
so okay one last question manasi says
what's the higs BOS on the higs BOS on
in the higs field is that it's it's a
fundamental particle that imparts Mass
to those fundamental particles that do
interact with it so the stronger a
particle the stronger fundamental
particle interacts with the higs field
The more mass it is more massive it is
and the less and the less strongly a
particle interacts with the Hig field
the less massive it is and some
particles simply don't interact with the
Hig field which is why they are massless
like the photon that's the higs boson
and the Hig
boson is part of the Hig field every
from the perspective of quantum field
Theory there are no particles it's only
fields and particles are simply local
excitations of the fields so how many
fundamental particles do we have the
standard Model 177+ 17 let's say 17 so
you have 17 different fields that
interact in various ways which give rise
to this illusory world that we live in
today this Maya that we live in today
but actually it's all Fields there are
no real
particles that's what it is okay I'm
going to end it over here thank you so
much everybody for all the questions I
really appreciate that I'm going to keep
on doing these science sessions as well
regularly so you can expect one next
week so yeah that's it for today I'm
going to have a history geopolitics
session tomorrow in case you want to
attend that please do and hopefully we
can we'll take questions of yours until
then thank you for watching have a good
day good night wherever you are and I'll
see you very soon bye-bye